Guide to the Arvid Paulson Papers 1875-1977 MSS.043
Fales Library and Special Collections
- Series II: Manuscripts
  - Subseries B: August Strindberg
    - Comrades (I) (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Comrades (II) (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Crimes and Crimes (I) (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Crimes and Crimes (II) (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Crimes and Crimes (III) (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Creditors (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - To Damascus, Part I. (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - The Dance of Death (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - A Dream Play (I) (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - A Dream Play (II) (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - A Dream Play (III) (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Easter (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Erik XIV (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - The First Warning (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - The Ghost Sonata (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - The Great Highway (I) (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - The Great Highway (II) (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - The Great Highway (III) (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - The Great Highway (IV) (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Hellas (Socrates) (Box 7, Folder 32)
    - Hermione (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - Hemsoborna (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - Jubal without a Self (Box 7, Folder 35)
    - Miss Julie (I) (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - Miss Julie (II) (Box 7, Folder 37)
    - The Lamb and the Beast (Box 7, Folder 38)
    - Letters to Harriet Bosse (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - Memorandum to the Members of the Intima Theatre (Box 7, Folder 40)
    - Modern Scandinavian Plays (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - Christ Trilogy (Box 7, Folder 42)
    - Moses / Through the Desert to Ancestral Lands (Box 7, Folder 43)
    - The Nightingale of Wittenberg (Box 7, Folder 44)
    - The Outlaw (Box 7, Folder 45)
    - The Pelican (Box 8, Folder 46)
    - Poems (Box 8, Folder 47)
    - The Scapegoat (I) (Box 8, Folder 48)
    - The Scapegoat (II) (Box 8, Folder 49)
    - The Scapegoat (III) (Box 8, Folder 50)
    - "Shakespeare's Outlook on Life" (Box 8, Folder 51)
    - Stormclouds (I) (Box 8, Folder 52)
    - Stormclouds (II) (Box 8, Folder 53)
    - The Stronger (Box 8, Folder 54)
    - Swanwhite (Box 8, Folder 55)
    - Vestman's Sealing Adventure (Box 8, Folder 56)
    - World Historical Plays (Box 8, Folder 57)
    - World Historical Plays (Box 8, Folder 58)
  - Subseries C: Paulson's mss. drafts for publication
    - Eight Expressionist Plays (I) (Box 9, Folder 59)
    - Eight Expressionist Plays (II) (Box 9, Folder 60)
    - Eight Expressionist Plays (III) (Box 9, Folder 61)
    - Eight Expressionist Plays (IV) (Box 9, Folder 62)
    - Eight Expressionist Plays (V) (Box 9, Folder 63)
    - The Natives of Hemso, Ch. I-IV (I) (Box 10, Folder 64)
    - The Natives of Hemso, Ch. V-VII (II) (Box 10, Folder 65)
    - The Natives of Hemso, Ch. I-IV (III) (Box 10, Folder 66)
    - The Natives of Hemso, Ch. V-VII (IV) (Box 10, Folder 67)
    - The Natives of Hemso, Ch. I-IV (V) (Box 10, Folder 68)
    - The Natives of Hemso, Ch. V-VII (VI) (Box 10, Folder 69)
    - The Natives of Hemso (VII) (Box 10, Folder 70)
    - One Act Prose Plays (I) (Box 11, Folder 71)
    - One Act Prose Plays (II) (Box 11, Folder 72)
    - One Act Prose Plays (III) (Box 11, Folder 73)
    - One Act Prose Plays (IV) (Box 11, Folder 74)
    - One Act Plays (I) (Box 11, Folder 75)
    - One Act Plays (II) (Box 11, Folder 76)
    - One Act Plays (III) (Box 11, Folder 77)
    - The Strindberg Reader (I) (Box 12, Folder 78)
    - The Strindberg Reader (II) (Box 12, Folder 79)
    - The Strindberg Reader (III) (Box 12, Folder 80)
    - The Strindberg Reader (IV) (Box 12, Folder 81)
    - The Strindberg Reader [proofs] (V) (Box 12, Folder 82)
  - Subseries D: Paulson's translations of Vilhelm Moberg, Knut Hamsun, Gustav Geijerstam and others.
    - Geijerstam, Gustav. Big Klaus and Little Klaus (I) (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Geijerstam, Gustav. Big Klaus and Little Klaus (II) (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Geijerstam, Gustav. Big Klaus and Little Klaus (III) (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Hamsun, Knut. Plays. (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Heden, Erik. Strindberg: An Index of his Achievement (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Moberg, Vilhelm. What's Yours is Mine. (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Oh, Olga. Judge Not! (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Prince Wilhelm of Sweden (I) (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Prince Wilhelm of Sweden (II) (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Subseries E: Miscellaneous Mss.
    - Summary of criticism on Strindberg's The Father (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Eyes in the Dark (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Fourth of July (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - The Grass (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - In the Dark (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Introductions (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - To Amandus Johnson, Pioneer (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - The Lady with the Leaking Valve / The Graft of Mrs. Plummer (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - One Less (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Poem by Paulson [xerox] (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - John Rockefeller as told by George Cohan (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - The Snake Pit (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Strindberg biography (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - A Swedish Captain (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - The Viking Flowers (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Lagerlof, Selma. The Hobgoblin of Toreby (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - Notes and Fragments of Plays (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - Berendsohn, Walter. Misc. Criticism (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - Mansfield, Richard. Poems. (Box 15, Folder 19)
    - Vowles, Richard B. Introduction to Strindberg (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - Charles XII (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - Unidentified mss., fragments (Box 15, Folder 22)
- Series III: Publications
  Series III contains criticism and translations published by Paulson and other writers in Swedish and American periodicals. Subseries A contains Paulson's articles on Strindberg, as well as Paulson's translations of Strindberg, Selma Lagerlof and Arvid Skappel. Subseries B contains articles on Strindberg and on Strindberg studies by other authors, as well as a 1913 translation of Strindberg's "Half a Sheet of Paper.
  - Subseries A: Paulson's published criticism
    - "On Translating Strindberg." The Performing Arts Review. 3:1, 1972 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - "August Strindberg, A Foe of Hypocrisy and Sham." Vasastjaernan. 55:5, 1962 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - "Henrik Ibsen." Equity, 1928 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - "Henrik Ibsen." The Scandinavian-American Bulletin. 13:3, 1968 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - "Probing Strindberg's Psyche." American-Scandinavian Review. 3:1, 1965 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - "Strindberg's Future in America." American-Swedish Historical Foundation Yearbook, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - "Strindberg's Pilgrimage Dramas, I-II." The Chronicle, 1954-1955 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Lagerlof, Selma. "The Hobgoblin of Toreby." World Fiction (Sept), 1922 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Skappel, Arvid. "Fresh Bread." World Fiction (Nov), 1922 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Strindberg, August. "Vestman's Sealing Adventure." The American-Scandinavian Review 54:1, 1966 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Strindberg, August. "Leontopolis." The American-Scandinavian Review 51:4, 1964 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Subseries B: Articles on Strindberg by other authors.
    - Androssy, Stella. "Uncle August: A Memoir of Strindberg." American Mercury 75:343, 1952 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Strindberg, August. "Half a Sheet of Paper." Trans. Velma Swanston Howard. American-Scandinavian Review 1:1 (Jan), 1913 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Wittrock, Ulf. "Strindberg och Heidenstams sista mote." Bonniers Litterar Magasin 18:5, 1949 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Bonniers Litterara Magasin (Strindberg Issue) 38:6, 1969 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Bonniers Manadshaften: Strindbergsnummer 6, 1912 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Bulletin of the American Swedish Institute: Strindberg Issue 4:3, 1949 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Meddelanden fran Strindbergssallskapet, no. 1-15, 1945-1953 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Meddelanden fran Strindbergssallskapet, no. 16-29, 1954-1961 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Meddelanden fran Strindbergssallskapet, no.s 30-31, 51-52, 1962/1963 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Modern Drama: Strindberg Issue 5:3 (Dec), 1962 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Berendsohn, Walter A. "Struktur- och stilanalysen: ett nodvandigt komplement till den svenska Strindbergsforskningen." Horisont 5, 1964 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Kungliga Dramatiska Teatern: Strindbergsjubileet (Strindberg issue), 1949 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Lindstrom, Goran. "Strindberg Studies, 1915-1962" Scandinavica 2:1, 1963 (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - Herrlin, Axel. "August Strindberg's Lundatid och hans dramatiska diktning: Nagra episoder." Skansk Kalender, 1936 (Box 18, Folder 14)
    - Theatre Arts: Swedish Theatre Issue (Aug) 23: 8 (Aug), 1940 (Box 18, Folder 15)
    - Gassner, John. "Strindberg in America." Theatre Arts 33:4 (May), 1949 (Box 18, Folder 16)
    - "Two Swedish Immortals: Strindberg and Lagerkvist" Tribute to Sweden (Nov), 1960 (Box 18, Folder 17)
    - Strindberg, August. "The Pelican." Trans. Evert Sprinchorn. The Tulane Drama Review 4:3, 1960 (Box 18, Folder 18)
    - World Theatre: Special Strindberg Issue 11:1, 1962 (Box 18, Folder 19)
    - Misc. Articles on Strindberg (Box 18, Folder 20)
- Series IV: Printed Matter and Memorabilia
  Series IV contains playbills, photographs, tickets, press clippings and other material from Paulson's life as a producer, performer and theater-goer; in addition it contains publicity material for his books and misc. Strindberg memorabilia. Subseries A contains playbills, photographs and tickets from performances of Strindberg's plays in Sweden and America, 1918-1979; Paulson either acted in or supplied the translations for some of these productions. Subseries A also contains misc. material from Paulson's life in the theatre, such as a 1941 manual for theatre staff and an assortment of actors' periodicals. Subseries B contains Strindberg memorabilia.
  - Subseries A: Playbills, photographs, tickets, periodicals, misc.
    - Playbills: Strindberg, 1918-1933 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Playbills: Strindberg, 1942-1949 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Playbills: Strindberg, 1952-1958 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Playbills: Strindberg, 1962-1969 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Playbills: Strindberg, 1970s (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Playbills: Paulson's own performances in Strindberg's plays; performances based on Paulson's translations, 1915-1970 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Press clippings: Strindberg's "The Great Highway", 1949/1952 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Photographs: Strindberg's "The Great Highway" (set design), 1949 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Photographs: Strindberg's "The Great Highway" (performance), 1952 (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - Photographs: Strindberg's "Brott och Brott" (set design), 1951 (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - Photographs: Strindberg's "Miss Julie" (performance), 1951/1958 (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - Photographs: Strindberg's "Stormclouds" (performance) (Box 19, Folder 12)
    - Photographs: misc. (performance), n.d. (Box 19, Folder 13)
    - Photographs, obituary: Richard and Beatrice Mansfield (actors), 1890s? (Box 19, Folder 14)
    - Photographs: (writer, actor and producer) Prins Wilhelm of Sweden, unknown woman (actress?), 1924, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 15)
    - Tickets, invitations: Performances of Strindberg and Ibsen, 1928, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 16)
    - Programs, invitations: Misc. Plays and Readings in which Paulson performed, 1915-1921 (Box 19, Folder 17)
    - Reviews: Paulson's productions and performances, 1920s-1930s (Box 19, Folder 18)
    - Program leaflets, invitations: Paulson reads from his Strindberg translations (Box 19, Folder 19)
    - Program leaflets, invitations, notes: Paulson reads from his Strindberg translations at the Library of Congress, 1962 (Box 19, Folder 20)
    - Misc. periodicals, publications about the theatre: "An Endowed Theatre," The Dramatist, (Actor's) Equity, The New Dawn, 1910-1934 (Box 19, Folder 21)
    - Misc. theatre material: "Theatre Annual" postcard (1943), "A Service Manual for Theatre Staff" (1941), "The Ten Commandments in Playwriting", 1940s (Box 19, Folder 22)
    - Press releases: Paulson's translations of Strindberg (Bantam and Phaedra), 1960-1970 (Box 19, Folder 23)
    - Reviews (extracts, typed quotes): Paulson's translations, 1950-1970 (Box 19, Folder 24)
    - Catalogues, lists: Svenska Forfattare (Bonniers), "Northern Literature" (Engberg-Holmberg), 1911 (Box 19, Folder 25)
    - Press Release: Strindberg's "Ockulta Dagboken" (Box 19, Folder 26)
  - Subseries B: Strindberg memorabilia
    - Photographs from a book: Strindberg's home, Strindberg at his desk, Strindberg writi (Box 19, Folder 27)
    - Photocopy of Strindberg's last will (handwritten; 23 March), 1911 (Box 19, Folder 28)
    - Postcards: Strindberg; paintings and library (Box 19, Folder 29)
    - Stamps: Strindberg stamps, 1949 (Box 19, Folder 30)
    - Strindberg: A Catalogue of his Paintings, from an exhibition at Gummesons Konsthall (8-31 Jan), 1924 (Box 19, Folder 31)
    - The Strindberg Museum: An Exhibition of Edward Munch's work, 1977 (Box 19, Folder 32)
    - The Strindberg Society: Membership List, 1955 (Box 19, Folder 33)
- Series V: Paulson's personal papers
  Series V contains Paulson's personal papers: photographs, awards, the mss. of a biography, calling cards and misc. legal papers.
  - Photographs: Arvid Paulson, 1933-1977 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Photographs: Misc. people, [1950]/1961 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Speech, notes: Paulson receives award from the Royal Swedish Academy of Letters, 1964 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Program leaflet: Paulson receives honorary degree from Upsala College, 1973 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Biography: Material assembled for an (auto-?)biography of Paulson (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Tickets and invitations to misc. events (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Calling Cards (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Legal Papers (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous: Magazines (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous: Maeterlinck quotations (typed) (Box 20, Folder 12)
- Oversize
  This series contains oversize material from the entire collection. Folders have been numbered according to the series sequence.
  - Series II, Subseries A: Mss. Ibsen, Peer Gynt (Box 21, Folder 12B)
  - Series II, Subseries A: Mss. Ibsen Memorial Speech (Box 21, Folder 18B)
  - Series II, Subseries A: Ibsen Productions in America, 1869-1916 (typed list) (Box 21, Folder 19B)
  - Series II, Subseries B: Strindberg's "Natives of Hemso" (galleys) (Box 21, Folder 70B)
  - Series II, Subseries D: Wilcox, Ella Wheeler. Mss. Poems. (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Series II, Subseries E: List of Strindberg's plays, 1869-1909. (Box 21, Folder 1B)
  - Series II, Subseries E: August Strindberg Poster, undated (Folder 2 Left)
  - Series II, Subseries E: People of America, 1940 (Folder 2 Left)
  - Series II, Subseries E: Voters of America, undated (Folder 2 Left)
  - Series II, Subseries E: "August Strindberg, Sweden's Strange Dramatist" in American Scandinavian, 1958 (Folder 2 Left)
  - Series II, Subseries E: Sketches, undated (Folder 2 Left)
  - Series III, Subseries B: Berg, John. "August Strindberg: En orientering i hans forfattarskap." Studiekamraten, 1949 (Box 21, Folder 21)
  - Series III, Subseries B: Misc. Articles on Strindberg (Box 21, Folder 22)
  - Series III, Subseries B: Obliques: The Strindberg Issue (Box 21, Folder 23)
  - Series III, Subseries B: Mansfield, Richard. "Little Theater in Big America." The Chronicle, 1917 (Box 21, Folder 24)
  - Series IV, Subseries A: Playbill: Ibsen, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 1A)
  - Series IV, Subseries A: Photograph: Strindberg's (?) "Gustav Vasa" (performance) (Box 21, Folder 13B)
  - Series IV, Subseries A: Photograph: Actor in role as Chinese...?, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 15B)
  - Series IV, Subseries A: Interview with Paulson about "Peer Gynt" (script), 1938 (Box 21, Folder 19B)
  - Series IV, Subseries A: Program, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 22C)
  - Series IV, Subseries B: Strindberg photo book (photos extracted) (Box 21, Folder 27A)
  - Series IV, Subseries B: Strindberg Book Jackets (Box 21, Folder 27B)
  - Series IV, Subseries B: Copy of Strindberg's mss. for "Branda Tomten", 1907 (Box 21, Folder 28B)
  - Series V: Paulson's Medal from the Royal Swedish Academy (Box 21, Folder 3B)
  - Series V: Paulson's original mss., "Armistice Day" and "Union Soldier" (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Series V: Biographical material on Paulson (Box 21, Folder 6B)
  - Series V: Paulson's notes for his "Strindberg Collections" (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Series V: Miscellaneous: Flyer (Roosevelt v. Wilkie) (Box 21, Folder 13)